<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great charity of instructing poor children A sermon preached at St. Botolph Aldgate; upon Lord's-day, Mar. 24. 1700. On the occasion of a charity-school newly erected in that parish. By Josiah Woodward, minister of Popler.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832429</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832429</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2143:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great charity of instructing poor children A sermon preached at St. Botolph Aldgate; upon Lord's-day, Mar. 24. 1700. On the occasion of a charity-school newly erected in that parish. By Josiah Woodward, minister of Popler.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], vi, 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by K. Astwood, for Ra. Sympson, at the Harp in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Durham Cathedral Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs V, 23 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Charity --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charity --  England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor children --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Charity of Inſtructing Poor Children.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED At St. <hi>Botolph Aldgate;</hi> UPON LORD'S-DAY, <hi>Mar.</hi> 24. 1700. On the Occaſion of A Charity-School Newly Erected in that Pariſh.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSIAH WOODWARD,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Popler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>K. Aſtwood,</hi> for <hi>Ra. Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> at the <hi>Harp</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36902:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:36902:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>Guilford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT Noble Delight and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry wherewith your Lordſhip ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances the Knowledge and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, demonſtrates the Honour that <hi>Almighty God</hi> does You, in making You Eminent in that Work, for which <hi>He ſent his Son into the World.</hi> And on this Account, thoſe <hi>Schools of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> which your Lordſhip, together with Other <hi>Perſons</hi> of great <hi>Worth and Quality,</hi> have ſtudiouſly Advanced in this City and other Parts; thoſe <hi>Good Books</hi> which are by theſe Means diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into poor Families; and thoſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techetical Libraries</hi> which are about to
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:36902:3"/> be compiled in this <hi>Nation</hi> and our <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> abroad, will be acknowledged with ſenſible Reſpect and Gratitude, by all but ſuch as have ſlight Thoughts of the Benefits, of <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh to deſtroy the Works of the Devil:</hi> Which is ſuch a Pitch of Groſs and Odious Inſenſibleneſs, as one would hope, could never have appear'd in a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Land;</hi> but yet, alas! we have too many Notorious Inſtances of it, thro' the deſperate Depravity of Men in their <hi>Minds</hi> and <hi>Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I KNOW, I need not mind your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, tho' ſome others cannot be call'd upon too often to Conſider it, That our <hi>Adored Lord and Saviour,</hi> aroſe as a <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs and Truth,</hi> to give Light and Warmth to this Dark and Degenerate World: And that the Splendid Beams of his <hi>Glorious Goſpel</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel the <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 20. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Candles</hi> of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon, and thoſe <hi>Tapers</hi> which the
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:36902:3"/> beſt <hi>Philoſophers</hi> held forth to Men; as much as the Glorious Sun exceeds thoſe Twinkling Lamps and Torches, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we endeavour to ſupply its abſent Light: Yet, alas! thro' the Depravity of Humane Underſtanding, and Men's <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning Love of Darkneſs more than Light;</hi> We find ſome, like the <hi>Moles</hi> and <hi>Bats,</hi> declining the Splendor of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation,</hi> and doting on the Dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Humane Reaſon:</hi> Saying with <hi>Philoſtratus, Porphirie,</hi> and the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Humaniſts,</hi> or rather with <hi>Julian</hi> and former <hi>Apoſtates, Let my Soul take its Riſque with Philoſophers,</hi> and the Followers of Natural Reaſon; rather than with the Diſciples of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion,</hi> and the Admirers of the <hi>Book which God ſent from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Like the wayward <hi>Jews,</hi> who were for deſerting the <hi>Pillar of Heavenly Fire,</hi> which led them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and conſpired to make a <hi>Captain</hi> of their own,
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:36902:4"/> who might lead them back into <hi>Egyptian Darkneſs</hi> again. An amazing Choice! and what cannot otherwiſe be accounted for, but by what the Apoſtle hath told us;<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> Namely, That <hi>If the Goſpel be hid, 'tis hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this World hath blinded the Minds of them that believe not; leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine into them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE ſee indeed with ſorrowful Hearts, that it pleaſes God, to permit the Legions of the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>Kingdom of his Dear Son.</hi> And in this great and general Conteſt, all Men upon Earth are engaged on one ſide, or other: For our <hi>Saviour</hi> has declared <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12. 30.</note> that none can be conſidered as <hi>Neuters,</hi> but that <hi>Such as are not with him, are againſt him.</hi> And tho' there be but few of the Devil's
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:36902:4"/> Confederates, that are hardy enough to own the ſide they take, but call it the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Humane Liberty,</hi> or ſome ſuch Thing; yet, alas! they buſily do the Devil's Work, they ſap the very Foundations of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> (which is the only true) and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Authority of its <hi>Sacred Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT is therefore, My Lord, to the great Honour of God, and the great Comfort of devout Minds, that we find ſome <hi>Perſons</hi> of Eminent <hi>Rank, Piety</hi> and <hi>Honour;</hi> who in the Vigor of Youth, in the Height of Worldly Blandiſhments, and in the Crowds of Corrupt Examples, bravely Trampling on <hi>All</hi> that the Uſurping <hi>God of this World</hi> can offer, to draw them to his Party; and who in Chriſtian Zeal for the <hi>Prince of Light,</hi> oppoſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Encroachments of the Spirits of Darkneſs, and are daily inſtrumental in diſcovering to ignorant Souls, the certain Paths which lead to <hi>Eternal Light
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:36902:5"/> and Bliſs.</hi> In which Glorious Work, Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the <hi>Worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> with You, are very happily engag'd, and will certainly find the Bleſſed Account of it, in the Accompliſhment of thoſe <hi>Great and Precious Promiſes,</hi> which are made to ſuch as glorifie their Creator, and adminiſter to the Salvation of Men; which are Things moſt truly Great and Noble, for which a Wiſe Man would chiefly wiſh to Live, and a Good Man would not grudge to Die. And that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> may long be ſucceſsful in theſe <hi>Divine Enterprizes,</hi> and at laſt reap the <hi>Immortal Glory</hi> of them, Is the Earneſt Deſire and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honour's</hi> Moſt Reſpectful AND Obedient, Humble Servant, Joſiah Woodward.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36902:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. V. 23.</bibl>
               <q>He ſhall die without Inſtruction, and in the greatneſs of his Folly, He ſhall go aſtray.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>SOLOMON,</hi> Who had a very Virtuous Education, and was Honour'd with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Communion with God in his Youth, was inſpired by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (in his Infinite Love to the Souls of Men) to write this Book of <hi>Proverbs</hi> for the <hi>Inſtruction of Youth;</hi> as he tells us in the beginning of the Book (<hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 4.) <hi>To teach the Young Man Knowledge and Diſcretion:</hi> That is, to ſhew them how bleſſed it is to be Religious betimes, and to Embrace thoſe Principles of Wiſdom and Virtue, which all that deſpiſe them in their Youth come to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their Age; crying out in the Bitterneſs of their Spirit at laſt, <hi>How have I hated Inſtruction, and my Heart deſpiſed Reproof!</hi> Prov. 5. 12.</p>
            <p>WE are therefore, to Conſider this <hi>Wiſe Prince</hi> as a Tutor to Youth in this Chapter, and we ſee, he begins it like a <hi>Grave Catechiſt</hi> to his
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:36902:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36902:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36902:7"/> Children; <hi>My Son, attend unto my Wiſdom, and bow thine Ear to my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi> (Ver. 1.) In which he intimates, That ſince he ſpake to them from the Bowels of a Father, and in the Wiſdom of God, all Young Perſons (however conceited of their own Wit, and addicted to their own Will, as Youth is apt to be) ought to ſubmit, and bow their Minds and Hearts to his <hi>Divine and Fatherly Inſtructions.</hi> And know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Unſteadineſs of Youth in Virtuous Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, to Engage them more firmly herein, he ſhews them in the Sequel of the Chapter; to what a Deplorable Condition ſuch Young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons uſually come, who ſlight the Counſels of their Parents and Friends; and run into thoſe Exceſſes, to which their <hi>Youthful Luſts</hi> prompt them. He inſtances in the Luſt of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> and inſiſts upon it throughout the greateſt part of this Chapter; diſſwading young People from it, with all the <hi>Argument</hi> and <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> that the Matter can be preſt: Shewing, that it is a <hi>Deep Pit,</hi> in which People bury their <hi>All</hi> at once. It being a Vice that blinds the Mind, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the Conſcience, hardens the Heart, and gives ſuch an Arbitrary Power to the Senſual Faculties, as over-bears all that's Good. And he tells them, that tho' the beginning of ſuch ſinful Ways ſeems <hi>Smooth as Oyl, and Sweet as Honey,</hi> (which is all that can be ſaid for them) yet they appear in the End <hi>as bitter as Wormwood, and ſharp as a two edged Sword; being the direct Road to Hell,</hi> and to Eternal Weeping and Wailing. For, as the poor wandring Youth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36902:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>hates Inſtruction,</hi> and will not bear Reſtraint, but counts thoſe his Enemies who ſhew him his Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and admoniſh him to do better, he comes at laſt to that dreadful Caſe foretold in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> to be abandoned of God, and in a great meaſure forſaken of the <hi>Spirit of Light and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> and ſo he <hi>dies without Inſtruction, and in the greatneſs of his Folly, he goes aſtray.</hi> The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſays here, it <hi>ſhall</hi> be ſo with him; intimating, that this is the uſual End of ſuch a Vicious and Profligate Youth, he comes moſt commonly to this Tragical <hi>Exit</hi> and Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Namely, to dye as wretchedly as he lived, and to go off his Stage of Vice and Vanity, in Horror and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>THIS is the dreadfuleſt Thing under the Sun. To die without the <hi>Knowledge of God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which is <hi>Life Eternal!</hi> to be given up to the <hi>Spirits of Darkneſs!</hi> and to be led Captive in their <hi>Chains,</hi> and hoodwink'd by their <hi>Deluſions,</hi> 'till he comes to be involv'd and immers'd in their <hi>Torments!</hi> This is the Depth of the Miſery of Man.</p>
            <p>WHAT Parent will not find their Bowels pained, to conſider this as the Caſe of any of their Children? You could not bear it, to ſee a <hi>Lion</hi> or a <hi>Bear</hi> ſnatch up a Child of yours in its Devouring Mouth, and carry it off as its Prey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You cannot bear the very Thoughts of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's Appearance in ſome Horrible Shape, and carrying away your Child in a Viſible Manner, before your Eyes: Yet, alas! how many Parents permit the Devil (that <hi>Roaring and Devouring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36902:8"/> Lion,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls him) to ſeize their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a way as certain and as terrible, tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not ſo Viſible.</p>
            <p>THEY hear their Children blaſpheming God, and offending him daily, groſly and familiarly; by the ſuggeſtion of the Devil (which demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates them to be under his Power and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement) yet ſome laugh at all this, and there are but few that are duely concern'd about it. How few are effectually awaken'd to teach their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren their <hi>Catechiſm</hi> and the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> that they may gird them with that <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> whereby they may defend themſelves from the malicious Fury of <hi>Apoſtate Spirits?</hi> How few are concern'd to teach their Children, the Way to Eternal Bliſs, thro' a Converting Faith in our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that they may not thro' the <hi>Greatneſs of their Folly,</hi> and Groſsneſs of their Ignorance <hi>go aſtray;</hi> and plunge themſelves into the Pit of Eternal Miſery?</p>
            <p>WHERE there is this pernicious Neglect of Catechizing in Parents, and ſuch as have the Over-ſight of Youth, it is an Error which is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom corrected by Sermons afterwards; becauſe they know not the very Terms and Language of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> nor the firſt Rudiments and Principles of <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine.</hi> And thus, alas! the Text comes to be dreadfully exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; <hi>They die without Inſtruction:</hi> They knew not the Lord and Saviour of Men in his ſaving Offices, and are ignorant of their own ſinful and periſhing Condition, and of the Terms on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36902:8"/> which Salvation is offer'd them; and ſo, they live and die in deſtructive Ignorance, and go aſtray from the Fold of the <hi>True Shepherd,</hi> and fall a Prey into the Mouth of <hi>Him, that lies in wait to devour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS is, methinks, one of the moſt moving Caſes that one can think of, and calls the loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt for <hi>Chriſtian Compaſſion;</hi> and therefore I ſhall further Explain it in the Following <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. ALL Perſons are born in a State of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Darkneſs as to Spiritual Things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the due Knowledge of God, and having no ſuitable Concernment about the Things which belong to their Everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. The Text ſuppoſes, that all Young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons need <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and that 'tis the Dreadfuleſt Thing in the World to die without it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Good <hi>Inſtruction</hi> in Youth is God's appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Means, to bring People to the ſaving Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf, and the Attainment of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The whole Deſign of this Book verifies this, and 'tis expreſt in a multitude of places throughout it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Neglect of Early Inſtruction and good Education, is the Ruine of many a Perſon in both Worlds. They live viciouſly, and die deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately; they paſs from the Errors and Works of Darkneſs, to the place of Utter and Eternal Darkneſs. <hi>They die without Inſtruction, and go aſtray,</hi> and periſh in their Ignorance and Folly.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:36902:9"/>
            <p>I. LET us in the firſt place Conſider that which I firſt Obſerved, <hi>Namely,</hi> That all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are born in a State of <hi>Ignorance and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as to Spiritual Things, being without the due Knowledge of God and the Way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Text ſuppoſes, that all Young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons need <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and that it is the dreadfuleſt Thing in the World to dye without it: And conſequently, that Pious Inſtruction is the moſt ſeaſonable Bleſſing that can come to any one in his Youth.</p>
            <p>'TIS well Obſerv'd by <hi>Zophar,</hi> one of <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>Friends</hi> (Job 11. 12.) that <hi>Man is born as the Wild Aſs</hi>'s <hi>Colt,</hi> utterly Rude and Unuſeful, except it be brought up to Hand, by a very Early and Careful Management; and then it is of great Uſe and Advantage to us. And we ſee it plainly ſo in our Children. If they are left to themſelves they are rude, froward, ſtubborn, wanton, undutiful and unmannerly. Like a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected Garden, which brings forth Weeds of it ſelf; but needs great Care and Pains to ſtore it with uſeful Plants.</p>
            <p>THERE is, Alas! a general Corruption of Humane Nature, ever ſince the Apoſtacy of our <hi>firſt Parents. We our ſelves alſo</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>were ſometime fooliſh, diſobedient, deceived, ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divers Luſts and Pleaſures.</hi> (Tit. 3. 3.) 'till the <hi>Love of God his Saviour appear'd to him</hi> by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Illumination. And ſo it is with us all 'till the Grace of God makes us better. For <hi>God is the Father of Lights, and the Author of every good
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36902:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and perfect Gift,</hi> (Jam. 1. 17.) and we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to <hi>Ask ſpiritual Wiſdom and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of him.</hi> (Ver. 5.)</p>
            <p>IF any doubt of this, Let him Conſider, whence it is, that ſuch a Reaſonable Creature as <hi>Man,</hi> ſhould delight in Things ſo Unfit and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper as all the Ways of Vice are? Whence is it, that Children need no Teacher to lead them to Lying, Pride and Stubbornneſs? Whereas they need much Inſtruction and Correction too, mingl'd with many Promiſes and Allurements; to bring them to that which is Good and Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? Yea, whence is it, that all Men do not Naturally delight in God above all other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſince He is undeniably the Beſt and moſt Excellent of Beings? Theſe are Demonſtrations of the <hi>Corruption of Man,</hi> and of the Neceſſity of <hi>Spiritual Regeneration</hi> by the Spirit of God; bringing him to love and delight in God, in the ſincerity of his Soul, e're he can be fit for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the nearer Preſence of God. Our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> hath delivered this with a double Aſſeveration (<hi>John 3. 5.) Verily, Verily, I ſay unto you, Except a Man be born again of Water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> The <hi>Spirit of Wiſdom</hi> muſt clear up his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the <hi>Spirit of Holineſs</hi> muſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his vile Affections and Paſſions, and turn the Bent and Vigor of his Heart towards God as his Chiefeſt Good; or he will not be fit for the Divine State and Work of Heaven, but will be barr'd out of it by the Nature and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that All Pure and God-like State.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36902:10"/>
            <p>AND this our Natural State of Spiritual Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is too groſs, and too deep to be removed and remedied by the beſt Light that <hi>Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy</hi> and Humane <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Study</hi> can ſupply us withal, We need a <hi>Light from Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom from Above,</hi> to make us <hi>Wiſe unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For, <hi>When in the Wiſdom of God</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the conceited <hi>Greek Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> which was then in great Vogue and Eſteem) <hi>the World by Wiſdom knew not God:</hi> That is, (I conceive); when God in his Infinite Wiſdom ſaw, that all the Humane Wiſdom and Learning in the World, would never bring them to the juſt and ſaving Knowledge of himſelf, as a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God; yet pardoning and juſtifying a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinner. <hi>It then pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching,</hi> (or by that plain but powerful Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of thoſe times accounted fooliſh) <hi>to ſave them that believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MEN have indeed by the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> ſome Knowledge, That there is a God and a Life to come. But how imperfect this Knowledge is, we ſee by the many abſurd Opinions and barbarous Cuſtoms of all thoſe <hi>Heathen Countries,</hi> which are not bleſs'd with the Knowledge of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> They frame to themſelves moſt unworthy notions of God, they know not how to worſhip or ſerve him aright; they have no Apprehenſion of the only way of being <hi>reconciled</hi> to God, by the <hi>Blood of his Son,</hi> nor of becoming Good through the <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of this Spirit.</hi> Yea, we find ſome of them profeſs'd Votaries to the Devil, and doing Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36902:10"/> to their worſt Enemy by the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Murders and Barbarities. Hence the Apoſtle concludes concerning the unregenerate Part of Mankind, that they <hi>Walk in the Vanity of their Minds, having their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; being alienated from the Life of God, thro' the Ignorance that is in them,</hi> Eph. 4. 18.</p>
            <p>WE may from all this aſſuredly diſcern, what ſort of Lives ſuch Children are like to live; who are not well <hi>Inſtructed, Catechized</hi> and <hi>Govern'd</hi> in their Youth. <hi>That which is born of the Fleſh is fleſh,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> (John 3. 6.) Carnal Principles will produce nothing better than a Carnal Life. So then, ſince Children have none but bad Principles and Inclinations of themſelves; what can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from them, but the greateſt Lewdneſs and the blackeſt Impieties; except thro' the Grace of God, and the Care of others, they are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter principled? Eſpecially if we conſider, How buſie and crafty the Devil will always be, to prompt them to all Wickedneſs; whilſt alas! the poor Child is utterly <hi>Ignorant of his Devices.</hi> So that a Youth without Inſtruction will be like a benighted Traveller, walking alone in the midſt of unknown Pits and Precipices; 'tis a Thouſand to one, but he falls into ſome of them to his utter Ruine.</p>
            <p>BUT it is God's Will that it ſhould be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and it ſhould be the Care of all that love and fear God, to bring up their Children in the Knowledge and Service of <hi>their Creator, in the Days of their Youth;</hi> that they may ſhun the dreadful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36902:11"/> Caſe of the Text, which leads me to the <hi>Second Obſervation.</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>II. THAT good <hi>Inſtruction in Youth</hi> is God's appointed Means, to bring People to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Knowledge of Himſelf; and the Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Eternal Life. God is pleaſed to call to Young People in the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to bow their Ear to <hi>Good Inſtruction,</hi> that they come not to the <hi>Dreadful End,</hi> foreſhewn in the End of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>INDEED, the Time of Youth is the moſt proper Time in <hi>Nature</hi> for good Inſtruction. Children are apt to catch at every Thing they hear, and to retain it, and repeat it. Their Faculties are freſh and vigorous; and they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves void of Knowledge, and are greedy to take Information, and ſoft and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any Impreſſion. They are alſo void of thoſe Prejudices againſt Truth and Virtue, which they are afterwards likely to take up. And they are not now capable of ſuch bodily Labour, as is apt to hinder their Learning in their more Adult Years. On all theſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, the Time of Youth is the fitteſt of any for <hi>good Inſtruction;</hi> and the propereſt Seaſon to plant the <hi>Principles of Religion.</hi> And that chiefly, becauſe 'tis God's Time, and muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of Neceſſity be the fitteſt and beſt. The Commandments of God do often bind this Duty very awfully, on the Conſciences both of <hi>Parents</hi> to teach their Children; and upon <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> to mind the Inſtruction of their Parents and Tutors. Parents are required to <hi>Train up
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36902:11"/> their Children in the Way that they ſhould go;</hi> (Prov. 22. 6.) and Children are required to <hi>Obey their Parents in the Lord.</hi> (Eph. 6. 1.) Parents are to <hi>Bring them up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord.</hi> (Eph. 6. 4.) And Children are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>Keep the Commandment of their Father, and not to forſake the Law of their Mother,</hi> (Prov. 6. 20.)</p>
            <p>AND theſe Injunctions are enforced by the higheſt Promiſes and Threatnings. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tells us, that the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi> is the <hi>Firſt Commandment with Promiſe; That it may be well with thee, and that thou mayſt live long on the Earth.</hi> (Eph. 6. 2, 3.) And on the contrary, it is threatned; That <hi>The Eye that mocketh his Father, or deſpiſeth to obey his Mother, the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of the Vallies ſhall pick it out, and the young Eagles ſhall cat it.</hi> (Prov. 30. 17.) And ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to all this, we find the Mother and Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother of <hi>Timothy,</hi> commended by the Spirit of God, for inſtructing their Child in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and <hi>Timothy</hi> is commended for his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, ſuitable to his Education. As we read in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to him.</p>
            <p>AND be it here Obſerved, That if any one is not taught to <hi>Read,</hi> and to know his <hi>Catechiſm</hi> in his Youth; 'tis a Thouſand to One, whether ever he learns either of theſe afterwards. The Senſleſs Pride of an Ignorant Perſon, is apt to diſdain Inſtruction in theſe Things afterwards; and they are utterly aſhamed, to acknowledge themſelves ignorant of that, in which they perceive, many little Children able to be their Tutors. So that we cannot be too ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36902:12"/> with all Parents, and ſuch as have the Management of Children, that they begin early to inſtruct them in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and in their <hi>Catochiſms;</hi> and that they take Care that they learn to read betimes, that they may of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Draw water out of the Wells of Salvation.</hi> For it is a moſt deplorable and moving Caſe, that God ſhould ſend us a Book from Heaven, concerning our Eternal Salvation; and that any among us ſhould ſay, as thoſe (<hi>Iſa. 29. 12.) I cannot read it, for I am not learned:</hi> Tis written in unknown Characters as to me, becauſe I was never taught to read. We many times now hear, ſuch Ignorant Perſons blaming their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for neglecting them in their Youth; when they come to perceive the want of ſuch Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they might have attained in their Youth; and tis to be feared, that too many ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, will hear the more doleful Accuſations and Curſes of their wretched Children, in their Torments hereafter. Where it may probably be ſaid by many a Perſon, had my Parents taught me better, I might have eſcaped theſe <hi>Everlaſting Burnings.</hi> This leads me to my <hi>Third Obſervation.</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>III. THAT the Neglect of Good Education and Early Inſtruction, is the Ruine of many a Perſon in both Worlds. 'They are brought up negligently<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they live viciouſly, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dye deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately. This was ſo ſadly verify'd in the Caſe of <hi>Eli</hi>'s Sons, (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.) that tis enough to terrifie every ſenſible Perſon out of ſuch Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect. His Sons were firſt <hi>Children of Darkneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:36902:12"/> then <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> and then <hi>Sons of Perdition.</hi> And thus, alas! it uſually fares with Uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, Ungovern'd and Uncatechiz'd Children; as it will further appear in the five following Particulars; which demonſtrate the diſmal Caſe of Ignorant and Undiſciplin'd Youth.</p>
            <p>(1.) THEY cannot live as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> if they know not the Fundamentals of the Chriſtian <hi>Religion.</hi> A Man can act no better than his Principles dictate to him. And ſuch as are not taught the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion, are never like to have them. An expreſs Faith in our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is neceſſary to the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a Chriſtian, (<hi>Mar. 16. 16.) He that believeth not ſhall be damned.</hi> But how can they <hi>Believe on him, of whom they have not heard?</hi> How can they come to know the <hi>Perſon,</hi> the <hi>Offices,</hi> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and the <hi>Will</hi> of our Lord and Saviour; except they learn it by the Inſtruction of their Parents and Friends, out of their <hi>Bibles</hi> and <hi>Catechiſms?</hi> 'Tis true, the Foundation of the Sacred <hi>Morals</hi> of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is laid in <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf, and the Equity, Fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Reaſonableneſs of them is diſcernable by Natural Light. For, <hi>Why of your ſelves judge ye not that which is right?</hi> Says our Bleſſed Lord, (<hi>Luke</hi> 12. 57.) But then, the Light of Nature is ſo dim and faint, that it will ſoon be obſcured and overlaid by ſinful Cuſtoms; and if the <hi>Light which is in Men be darkneſs, how groſs is that Darkneſs!</hi> (Mat 6. 23.) How extravagantly vicious will thoſe Affections and Paſſions be, which have no Light by which they may ſteer; and no good Principles from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36902:13"/> which they may act? Such uncatechized Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, I ſay, cannot be good Chriſtians; yea, they uſually prove the worſt of Men. For,</p>
            <p>(2.) For want of being grounded in the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials of Chriſtian Doctrine, they are eaſily miſled into any <hi>Error</hi> or <hi>Hereſie.</hi> It may be Obſerved, that there. was ſcarce ever any fooliſh Opinion ſtarted, but the vain Author found ſome, as vain as himſelf to follow him in it. As in the Caſe of <hi>Mahomet, Mugleton</hi> and others. And it can be nothing but Ignorance, that is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſuch Devotion: The Ignorant catch at any thing. And hence proceed thoſe Unhappy <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Parties</hi> that are among us; which is in a great meaſure owing to the want of due Catechizing. <hi>The Enemy ſowed Tares,</hi> whilſt thoſe were <hi>aſleep,</hi> that ſhould have ſown better Grain.</p>
            <p>(3.) Theſe Undiſciplin'd and Uncatechized Perſons uſually prove ill Members of the <hi>State;</hi> and the very Peſt of the Neighbourhood, in which they live. One may indeed call them, the very Vermine of the Publick Body. Hence come thoſe Swarms of idle, pilfering and purloining People, of which we hear daily Complaints, and feel the diſmal Effects. Some of which are ſo crafty in their Devices, and ſo harden'd in their Wickedneſs, that they ſeem to be the very <hi>Black Guard</hi> of the Prince of Darkneſs; and a fruitful Nurſery of a ſort of People, which fill the Goals and load the <hi>Gallows.</hi> A very ſad, but a very great Truth.</p>
            <p>(4.) Theſe Untaught and Uneducated People are they, who chiefly bring a Reproach on our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36902:13"/> Religion, and the <hi>Church of Chriſt amongſt us.</hi> They live like Infidels in a Chriſtian Land: And many of them being bred up to no Employment at Home, are forc'd by their Neceſſities to ſeek their Bread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abroad; and ſo they carry our Shame, together with their Villanies, into Forreign Parts. And many Forreigners take up a Prejudice againſt our <hi>Nation,</hi> and againſt our <hi>Religion,</hi> by what they ſee and ſuffer from theſe Profligates; which has proved a great Bar to the Progreſs of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(5.) THAT which is yet the moſt dreadful Thought of all, is, That the God that made them will reject them at the laſt. <hi>They are a People of no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah) therefore he that made them will not have Mercy upon them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no Favour.</hi> (Iſa. 27. 11.) They bear the <hi>Image and Superſcription</hi> of their Father, the Prince of Darkneſs; and will be adjudged to him by the juſt Judgment of him, <hi>In whom there is no Darkneſs at all.</hi> They have long lived in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance and Enmity to him, that came to be the <hi>Light and Life of the World;</hi> they hated the Light of the Goſpel, and the Guidance of his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; they have pleaſed themſelves with the Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Devil, and therefore they fall a Prey to him; as Apoſtates from their Creator: And as they <hi>loved Darkneſs more than Light,</hi> they muſt inevitably take their Portion in Eternal Darkneſs: For, <hi>They die without Inſtruction, and go aſtray from God,</hi> and his Beatifick Preſence.</p>
            <p>O Dreadful End, of ſuch as are neglected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36902:14"/> reformed! Enough to create Horror in every Soul that conſiders it. Who is there, that has any thing of the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt in him,</hi> that would not think a great part of his Care, Pains and Eſtate well laid out, if he may but be Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to ſave ſome few; yea, but one ſingle Perſon, from this Eternal Ruine? And that I may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline every one that hears me, to take this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and mournful Caſe into Conſideration, I now come to apply what has been ſaid.</p>
            <p>SINCE the Caſe of groſs Ignorance is thus dreadful and deplorable, We may ſee,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 1. To how Divine and Bleſſed a State the Holy Goſpel of our Lord tends to lead us! It comes to retrieve us from the deſtructive Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sin and Satan; to knock off the Fetters of the Prince of Darkneſs, who had led us <hi>Captive at his Will;</hi> and to tranſlate us to the <hi>Light and Liberty of the Sons of God.</hi> We may better ſpare the Light of the Sun, than that of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; for this is the Light of our Souls, and the Foundation of our Hope, and the Dawning of Everlaſting Light. Here we have perfect Truth, infinite Mercy, ſafe Directions, and ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations. We may challenge all the <hi>Philoſophy</hi> that ever appear'd in the Word, to give us ſo much <hi>Divinity,</hi> as we can view in one Chapter of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> and we are ſure that all the Riches of the whole World are not of ſuch Value, as one of the Promiſes of that Bleſſed Book. O that it were more frequently in our Hands, more deep in our Hearts, and more le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible in our Lives.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36902:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 2. SINCE the Caſe of groſs Ignorance is thus dreadful, what a conſtraining Argument is this to all Parents and Governours of Youth; to be very Early, very Conſcientious and Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Catechizing and Inſtructing their Children. One would think, that it were enough to drive Parents to Diſtraction, to think of any dying Child of theirs, as going to Eternal Miſery, for want of due Inſtruction. If any Parents ſhould ſtarve their Children, by denying them neceſſary Food when they have Plenty of it by them; the whole Neighbourhood would cry Shame on ſuch a dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Barbarity, and count them worthy of Death for it: And ſurely the Deſtruction of an <hi>Immortal Soul,</hi> will one Day appear as hateful and as Criminal. So that the Eaſe of their own Minds and Conſciences, ought to quicken Parents to this Duty; and beſides, they cannot reaſonably expect any Comfort in their Children, nor Duty from them, if they be not well inſtructed. We muſt carefully cultivate and manure our Fields, if we would reap a comfortable Hanveſt; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they will produce nothing but Weeds and Thorns to offend and wound us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infer.</hi> 3. SINCE the Caſe of groſs Ignorance and the want of Education is thus pernicious; What greater Charity can we ſhew to Humane Nature, than to contribute towards the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe; who will otherwiſe very probably die without it? <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that <hi>Inſtruction is rather to be choſen then Silver, and Knowledge rather than choice Gold,</hi> (Prov. 8. 10.) From which it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36902:15"/> That ſuch as educate their Children well are greater Friends to them than ſuch as leave them a Temporal Eſtate. For indeed, an Eſtate bequeathed to ſuch, as have neither Knowledge to uſe it well, nor Principles to do good with it; is like a Sword in the Hand of a Madman, with which he will be likely to do much harm to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and others. Whereas on the other Hand, Good Manners and Chriſtian Behaviour recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the meaneſt Perſon to all that know him; and that Good Providence which orders all things, will not leave them deſtitute of outward Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>Who ſeek the Kingdom of God in the firſt place.</hi> (Mat. 6. 33.)</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore, without Praiſe to God, turn my Eyes towards thoſe many Children before us; who at once adorn the Houſe of God, and ſhew forth the Honour of thoſe Perſons, by whoſe Care and Charity they are brought to <hi>Chriſtian Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Praiſed be God, who put ſo worthy a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign into the Minds of Men, and who has enlarged the Hearts of any to contribute generouſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it. This gives us ſome Hopes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of God's Mercies to us, eſpecially that Mercy of Mercies his <hi>Holy Goſpel.</hi> We hope, the next Generation will prize it more, and practiſe it better than this has done; <hi>That it may be well with them, and with their Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS ſhould prompt us, yea, bring us under a ſort of Neceſſity; to put forth our ſelves to the utmoſt to advance the Good Education of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to promote <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge</hi> in all others that want it; which we may do theſe three Ways.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36902:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> BY perſonal Conference: Taking Pains to inſtruct thoſe Children, and other Ignorant People, with whom we converſe, in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Great Things of God's Law;</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in thoſe practical and neceſſary Truths, in which the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of our Holy Religion conſiſt. Chriſtians are to be as <hi>Salt,</hi> to all that keep Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with them, to ſeaſon them with the Savour of Chriſtian Doctrine. This does indeed, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally concern <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are to be <hi>Burning and Shining Lights</hi> in their Generation; whoſe particular Viſits to the Houſes of their People, and perſonal Enquiry into their State and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life; is of very great Uſe to the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Religion in Families, and to excite that Chriſtian Affection to their Miniſter; which will make his Inſtructions the more effectual upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> ANOTHER Way of advancing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Inſtruction is, by giving and diſperſing good Books abroad in the World, eſpecially to poor Families. This may in ſome Caſes do more good than perſonal Diſcourſe, in that a good Book abides with the Perſon to whom it's given; and will lye before his Eyes at all Seaſons, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome Affliction or ſome other good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, may be a means to awaken and ſoften his Heart; and make it fit to receive Inſtruction, and to prize a Book of Devotion. And bleſſed be God, we have many <hi>Honourable and Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> happily engaged in this Excellent Work; which we muſt acknowledge to be one of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36902:16"/> beſt of Charities. And in this, thoſe that are Wealthy will do well to conſider, the Deplorable Caſe of our <hi>Plantations;</hi> in which moſt Chriſtian Work, a very <hi>Pious and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Bray.</note> 
               <hi>Perſon</hi> has adventured his <hi>All,</hi> with a ſort of <hi>Apoſtolick Charity</hi> to the Souls of Men. In this Noble Deſign, all that really love our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> cannot but pray to God to proſper him. Surely 'tis time for ſuch as love the Kingdom of God, and repeat the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Petition of the Lord's Prayer, (<hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come</hi>) to ſet themſelves in good earneſt, to retrench the Encroachments of the <hi>Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> WE may be inſtrumental to promote the Inſtruction of others, by contributing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Ability, towards the maintainance of poor Children at School; who may otherwiſe, thro' the Poverty of their Parents, be too likely to <hi>Dye without Inſtruction.</hi> And bleſſed be God, who hath ſo far enclined the Hearts of many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to conſider this; that there are now in and about this City, about a <hi>Thouſand poor Children</hi> taught to read, and inſtructed in their Catechiſms; and brought up to other Things, which tend to make them uſeful in their Generation; thro' the <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> of Well-diſpoſed Perſons. A moſt Excellent Work, towards which, all that duely know the Goſpel, cannot but be <hi>Glad to contribute,</hi> that they may ſhare the in vaſt Bleſſings that attend it.</p>
            <p>I am confident I need not tell you, that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity</hi> is neceſſary to a <hi>Chriſtian Life;</hi> ſince
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36902:16"/> the Apoſtle tells us, that all our other Works tho' never ſo ſplendid, <hi>will avail us nothing without Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> (1 Cor. 13.). And indeed, there are ſo many Commands in the Goſpel which require it, and ſo many Promiſes which enforce it, that we muſt quit our Chriſtian Faith if we renounce this Chriſtian Grace.</p>
            <p>SUPPOSING therefore, that your Chriſtian Breaſts glow with Charitable Affections and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; you have only two Things to look to in the Exerciſe of your Charity: Namely, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That you give to a good Deſign: And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> That you deliver it to ſuch Hands, as will faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully employ it according to your Intention.</p>
            <p>1. AS to the <hi>Firſt,</hi> Contribution towards the Teaching of Children to read, and to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them in the Principles of Religion and Virtue; is one of the moſt Extenſive, Good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, that we can readily think of. For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</p>
            <p>(1.) YOU'LL hereby prevent much Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World. You'll be likely to bring thoſe Lips to praiſe God, who might otherwiſe blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his Holy Name. You may hereby diminiſh, and we hope in the Progreſs of it, thin the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan, and increaſe and greaten the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Flock of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(2.) HEREBY, you take the likelieſt Way to make the meaner ſort of People uſeful in their Generation. Such as perhaps might otherwiſe have robb'd or injur'd you, may thro' <hi>Chriſtian Inſtruction</hi> become a faithful Servant to you, or an uſeful Artiſt by you, or an honeſt Neighbour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36902:17"/> near You: Yea, perhaps out of thoſe little Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of Virtue and Good Manners, there may ariſe ſome <hi>Eminent Citizens,</hi> who may themſelves be able to relieve others, and to be Benefactors to that place which was ſo careful of them, and bountiful to them in their Feeble and Helpleſs State.</p>
            <p>(3.) HEREBY, You adminiſter to them in the beſt ſort of Gifts. You become Eyes to the Blind, Knowledge to the Ignorant, Wiſdom to the Fooliſh; and perhaps Salvation to ſuch as might otherwiſe have periſh'd without Inſtruction. When we ſee a poor neglected Child groveling in a Dunghill, begging in the Streets, or wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in Wickedneſs: Let us Conſider, that this poor Creature has an <hi>Immortal Soul</hi> as well as we; yea, perhaps he has good Natural Parts, and if he were but well Educated, he might be of Great Uſe in his Generation. However, we are ſure he has a Soul <hi>for which Chriſt died;</hi> and might ſhare in the infinite Glories of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if due Care were taken of him. O! how can any Chriſtian Bowels but yearn over ſuch a Melting Object?</p>
            <p>IT was a particular Caſe very like to this, that moved the preſent Divinity-Profeſſor of <hi>Halle</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi> Dr. <hi>Franken;</hi> to compaſſionate the Ignorance of poor People, and by his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Intereſt to procure the Erecting of a Colledge, for the Maintainance and Inſtruction of about a hundred poor Children. But I muſt paſs on to what remains.</p>
            <p>(4.) AS by this Charity, you'll have many Prayers put up to Heaven for you; ſo what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36902:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Good they are brought to do thro' this their Virtuous Education, will in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure redound to your Account. For, <hi>Such as turn many to Righteouſneſs, will ſhine as the Stars for Ever and Ever.</hi> (Dan. 12. 3.)</p>
            <p>2. THIS clears the <hi>Firſt</hi> Point, Namely, The Goodneſs of the Deſign. And now as to the <hi>Second,</hi> Namely, Your being ſure that what you give, is faithfully diſpoſed of according to your Charitable Intention. Your own Eyes ſee it, in thoſe Comely Claſſes of Youth before You; and your Ears have heard the Proof of their Inſtruction, in the principal Doctrines of our Holy Religion. In which they give a good Example to other Youth, in the Exactneſs and Audibleneſs of their Anſwers, in their devout Behaviour, and their Melodious Singing of Pſalms; in which, I pray God incline all our Children to follow them.</p>
            <p>AND this minds me of an Act of <hi>Charity,</hi> in which Every One may contribute towards the Advancement of theſe Chriſtian Deſigns; Namely, In Hearty Prayer for God's Bleſſing upon them. In this, the pooreſt Perſon that is, may be a <hi>Benefactor.</hi> And Oh! May we all be Earneſt in Prayer to God, that it may pleaſe him to <hi>Fill the Earth with the Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour, as the Waters cover the Sea.</hi> That, as in the Sea, there is no Gap or Diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Expanded Waters; ſo there may be no Ignorance of <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> upon Earth; and ſo, no Ground whereon to Erect the Kingdom of Darkneſs. But that <hi>All Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36902:18"/> may know the Lord from the leaſt to the greateſt;</hi> from the Child that is coming into the World, to the Old Man that is going out of it; that ſo, none may incur the Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Doom of the Text; that is, <hi>To dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Inſtruction;</hi> and go aſtray from God and his Kingdom. Which God Almighty grant for the Sake of Jeſus Chriſt, who died to <hi>Turn us from Darkneſs to Light,</hi> and <hi>from the Power of Satan unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
